Chapter 4. the counterpay.
Upon waking next morning about daylight, I found Qui Quag's arm thrown over me in
the most loving and affectionate manner.
He had almost thought I had been his wife. The counterpane was of patchwork
full of odd little partycoled squares and triangles, and this arm of his
tattooed all over with an interminable labyrinth of a figure, no two
parts of which were of one precise shade, owing, I suppose, to his keeping
his arm at sea unmethodically in sun and shade, his shirt sleeves irregularly
rolled up at various times. This same arm of his, I say, looked for all the
world like a strip of that same patchwork quilt. Indeed, partly lying on
it as the arm did when I first awoke, I could hardly tell it from the quilt they
so blended their hues together, and it was only by the sense of weight and
pressure that I could tell that Quiquake was hugging me. My sensations were
strange. Let me try to explain them.
When I was a child, I well remember a somewhat similar circumstance that
befell me. Whether it was a reality or a dream, I never could entirely settle.
The circumstance was this. I had been cutting up some caper or other. I think
it was trying to crawl up the chimney, as I had seen a little sweep do a few
days previous, and my stepmother, who somehow or other was all the time
whipping me or sending me to bed supperless, my mother dragged me by the
legs out of the chimney and packed me off to bed, though it was only 2:00 in
the afternoon of the 21st June, the longest day of the year in our
hemisphere. I felt dreadfully, but there was no help for it. So upstairs I went
to my little room in the third floor, undressed myself as slowly as possible
so as to kill time, and with a bitter sigh, got between the sheets. I lay
there dismally calculating that 16 entire hours must elapse before I could
hope for a resurrection.
16 hours in bed. The small of my back achd to think of it, and it was so
light, too, the sun shining in at the window, and a great rattling of coaches
in the streets, and the sound of gay voices all over the house. I felt worse
and worse. At last I got up, dressed, and softly going down in my stocking
feet, sought out my stepmother, and suddenly threw myself at her feet,
beseeching her as a particular favor to give me a good slippering for my
misbehavior, anything indeed but condemning me to lie a bed such an
endurable length of time. But she was the best and most conscientious of
stepmothers, and back I had to go to my room. For several hours I lay there
broad awake, feeling a great deal worse than I have ever done since, even from
the greatest subsequent misfortunes.
At last I must have fallen into a troubled nightmare of a doze, and slowly
waking from it, half steeped in dreams, I opened my eyes, and the before sunlit
room was now wrapped in outer darkness.
Instantly I felt a shock running through all my frame. Nothing was to be seen and
nothing was to be heard, but a supernatural hand seemed placed in mine.
My arm hung over the counterpane, and the nameless, unimaginable, silent form
or phantom to which the hand belonged seemed closely seated by my bedside. For
what seemed ages piled on ages, I lay there frozen with the most awful fears,
not daring to drag away my hand. Yet, ever thinking that if I could but stir
at one single inch, the horrid spell would be broken. I knew not how this
consciousness at last glided away from me, but waking in the morning, I
shudderingly remembered it all, and for days and weeks and months afterwards, I
lost myself in confounding attempts to explain the mystery. Nay, to this very
hour I often puzzle myself with it. Now take away the awful fear, and my
sensations at feeling the supernatural hand in mine were very similar in their
stranges to those which I experienced on waking up and seeing Quequ's pagan arm
thrown around me. But at length all the past nights events soberly recurred one
by one in fixed reality, and then I lay only alive to the comical predicament.
For though I tried to move his arm, unlock his bridegroom clasp, yet
sleeping as he was, he still hugged me tightly as though not but death should
part us twain, I now strove to rouse him. Quiqu, but his only answer was a
snore. I then rolled over my neck, feeling as if it were in a horse collar,
and suddenly felt a slight scratch.
Throwing aside the counterpane, there lay the tomahawk, sleeping by the
savage's side, as if it were a hatchet-faced baby. A pretty pickle,
truly thought I, a bed here in a strange house in broad day with a cannibal and a
tomahawk. Quiquake.
At length, by dent of much wriggling, and loud and incessant expostations upon
the unbecomingness of his hugging a fellow male in that matrimonial sort of
style, I succeeded in extracting a grunt, and presently he drew back his
arm, shook himself all over like a Newfoundland dog, just from the water,
and sat up in bed, stiff as a pike staff, looking at me and rubbing his
eyes as if he did not altogether remember how I came to be there. though
a dim consciousness of knowing something about me seemed slowly dawning over him.
Meanwhile I lay quietly eyeing him, having no serious misgivings now, and
bent upon narrowly observing so curious a creature. When at last his mind seemed
made up, touching the character of his bedfellow, and he became, as it were,
reconciled to the fact, he jumped out upon the floor, and by certain signs and
sounds, gave me to understand that, if it pleased me, he would dress first, and
then leave me to dress afterward, leaving the whole apartment to myself.
Think I, Quiquake, under the circumstances, this is a very civilized
overture. But the truth is, these savages have an innate sense of
delicacy. Say what you will. It is marvelous how essentially polite they
are. I pay this particular compliment to Quiquake because he treated me with so
much civility and consideration while I was guilty of great rudeness, staring at
him from the bed and watching all of his twilelet motions. For the time my
curiosity getting the better of my breeding. Nevertheless, a man likewig
you don't see every day. He in his ways were well worth unusual regarding.
He commenced dressing at top by dawning his beaver hat, a very tall one by the
by, and then, still, minus his trousers, he hunted up his boots. What under the
heavens he did it for, I cannot tell.
But his next movement was to crush himself, boots in hand, and hat on,
under the bed, when, from sundry, violent gaspings and strainings, I
inferred he was hard at work booting himself, though by no law of propriety
that I ever heard of, is any man required to be private when putting on
his boots. But Quiquake, do you see was a creature in the transition stage,
neither caterpillar nor butterfly, he was just enough civilized to show off
his outlandishness in the strangest possible manners. His education was not
yet completed. He was an undergraduate.
If he had not been a small degree civilized, he probably would not have
troubled himself with boots at all. But then, if he had not been still a savage,
he never would have dreamt of getting under the bed to put them on. At last he
emerged with his hat very much dented and crushed down over his eyes and began
creaking and limping about the room as if not being much accustomed to boots.
His pair of damp, wrinkled cowhide ones, probably not made to order either,
rather pinched and tormented him at the first go off of a bitter cold morning.
Seeing now that there were no curtains to the window, and that the street being
very narrow, the house opposite commanded a plain view into the room,
and observing more and more the indecorous figure that Quiquake made,
staving about with little else but his hat and boots on, I begged him as well
as I could to accelerate his toilet somewhat, and particularly to get into
his pantaloons as soon as possible. He complied, and then proceeded to wash
himself. At that time in the morning any Christian would have washed his face,
but Quiquake, to my amazement, contented himself with restricting his ablutions
to his chest, arms, and hands. He then dawned his waist coat, and taking up a
piece of hard soap on the wash stand center table, dipped it into water, and
commenced lathering his face. I was washing to see where he kept his razor,
and lo and behold, he takes the harpoon from the bed corner, slips out the long
wooden stock, unshaths the head, wets it a little on his boot, and striding up to
the bit of mirror against the wall, begins a vigorous scraping, or rather
harpooning of his cheeks. Thinks I quiquake, this is using Roger's best
cutlery with a vengeance. Afterwards, I wondered less at this operation when I
came to know what fine steel the head of a harpoon is made, and how exceedingly
sharp the long, straight edges are always kept.
The rest of his toilet was soon achieved, and he proudly marched out of
the room, wrapped up in his great pilot monkey jacket, and sporting his harpoon
like a marshall's baton.